Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VI: The Cuban Excludables, 1989-1997; 477203
  - Smith, Wayne: Interview (part 2), circa 1990s; 479513 (Box 50, Cassette ref1171, Box 98, Dvd ref1171)
    This interview with American diplomat Wayne Smith begins with a discussion about Cubans attempting to cross the Strait of Florida on rafts, which transitions into a discussion about Cuban "excludable aliens." This part of the interview focuses on United States immigration policy toward Cuba, which Smith describes as a double standard when compared to countries like Haiti. He also discusses the US immigration policy that led to the detention of the Cuban "excludables," and criticizes the United States for not doing more to restore normal relations with Cuba. Smith discusses the political influence of the Miami Cuban community and expresses his disappointment that Cubans and American have not had the opportunity to communicate with each other for many years.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:21.
  - Smith, Wayne / Austin, Duke / Penalver, Rafael / Detainees: Interviews on Immigration, circa 1990s; 479437 (Box 48, Cassette ref1098, Box 98, Dvd ref1098)
    This video consists of three separate interviews with American diplomat Wayne Smith, Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) officer Duke Austin, and attorney Rafael Penalver. The three interviews focus on INS and US government policy that led to the detention of the Cuban "excludables." The interviews include discussion about the detention of Cuban "excludable aliens" from different perspectives, and include anecdotes about individuals held by US immigration services. The end of the video features a series of interviews with Cuban detainees after they were deported to Cuba. They discuss their treatment in American prisons and the events that led their detention.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:59:19.
  - Van Ness, Shela; Lawson, Earl, Sandidge, Sally; Dudeck, Carla: Interviews, circa 1990s; 467557 (Box 92, Cassette ref496, Box 82, Dvd ref496)
    This recording contains three separate interviews. The first interview is with criminology professor Shela Van Ness, who discusses the Talladega riots and her support of the detainees. In the second interview, Bravo speaks with Earl Lawson, a retired prison employee from Atlanta. In the final portion, Bravo interviews Sally Sandidge and Carla Dudeck, activists with the Coalition to Support Cuban Detainees.
  - Airport, 1992 January 30; 479448 (Box 63, Cassette ref1109)
  - Airport, circa 1990s; 479506 (Box 50, Cassette ref1164)
  - "Airport, Plane, Entering Bus, Pablo and Guillermo", circa 1990s; 479494 (Box 64, Cassette ref1152)
  - Airport Scenes and Interview Footage, circa 1990s; 467682 (Box 91, Cassette ref371, Box 80, Dvd ref371)
    This video contains footage of detainees boarding flights and arriving at a Cuban facility It features interviews with passengers in Spanish and footage of them boarding a plane. It contains an interview in English with a Department of Justice employee and interviews in Spanish with detainees during their flight.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:54.
  - "Atlanta Prison Doors, Hospital Interview", circa 1990s; 479476 (Box 64, Cassette ref1137)
  - "Block I": Airport Footage, circa 1990s; 467558 (Box 92, Cassette ref495, Box 82, Dvd ref495)
    The first 13 minutes of this video contain footage of Cuban detainees at an airport. The remainder of the tape contains an unrelated commercial recording.
  - "Block II": Interview Footage, Detainees, circa 1990s; 467662 (Box 92, Cassette ref391, Box 80, Dvd ref391)
    This footage contains interviews in Spanish with the detainees. The interviews discuss the prison experience and include discussions about abuse and Dr. Bolivar Martineau.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:59:00.
  - "Block III": Interview Footage with Detainees, circa 1990s; 467663 (Box 92, Cassette ref390, Box 80, Dvd ref390)
    This footage features interviews in Spanish with detainees on a bus. In one interview, a detainee discusses the difficulties of being separated from his son.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:32:00.
  - "Block IV": B-roll, circa 1990s; 467559 (Box 92, Cassette ref494, Box 82, Dvd ref494)
    This footage contains two sections of what appears to be B-roll of detainees at airport. The remainder contains footage of a speech, which is poor quality and difficult to view.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:49:00.
  - "Block V": Footage, Various, Including Walkiria Fernandez and Detainee Interviews, circa 1990s; 467562 (Box 92, Cassette ref491, Box 81, Dvd ref491, Box 82)
    In the first clip Walkiria Fernandez speaks to the detainees. The conversations are in Spanish. The screen cuts out between 00:14:44 and 00:16:22. Following the drop-out, there are additional interviews with detainees on bus and at airport. In their interviews they discuss general abuses at the prison and Dr. Martineau. The last ten minutes of the video is damaged and contains content that is difficult to view.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:00:00.
  - Bloque VI Visits with Families and Prisoners in Cuba, circa 1990s; 479436 (Box 63, Cassette ref1097)
  - "Block VII": Interview footage with Focus on Discussion of Dr. Martineau, circa 1990s; 467664 (Box 92, Cassette ref389, Box 80, Dvd ref389)
    This video contains interview footage of detainees talking about Dr. Bolivar Martineau. It includes interview with Cuban detainee who was assigned to work with Martineau. Some of this footage is in English.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:48:00.
  - Excludables Homecoming with Walkiria Fernandez, circa 1990s; 467730 (Box 91, Cassette ref323, Box 79, Dvd ref323)
    This recording contains footage of detainees being welcomed home by family members. It includes brief interviews with relatives of the detainees. It also features many scenes with Walkiria Fernandez. In the video, she accompanies returning detainees to Cuba and explains what the men experienced to a number of individuals on the street.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:57:18.
  - Excludables Homecoming, Street Scenes with Walkiria Fernandez, circa 1990s; 467718 (Box 91, Cassette ref335, Box 80, Dvd ref335)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:00:04.
  - "ESSAIS #1 - Missile - Wayne Smith", undated; 479739 (Box 49, Cassette ref1392)
  - Footage with Walkiria Fernandez, circa 1990s; 467680 (Box 91, Cassette ref373, Box 80, Dvd ref373)
    The first few minutes (approximately 4 minutes) includes scenes of Walkiria Fernandez and detainees. This is followed by footage unrelated to the documentary.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:17:31.
  - Footage: Dr. Martineau, circa 1990s; 467556 (Box 88, Cassette ref497, Box 82, Dvd ref497)
    The footage is composed of either Dr. Martineau speaking or being spoken about. In many parts there is a loud Spanish narration that overpowers the English. In some cases there is Spanish over Spanish.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:10:00.
  - Footage: Homecoming Scenes, circa 1990s; 467725 (Box 91, Cassette ref328, Box 79, Dvd ref328)
    This footage duplicates previous homecoming scenes. This is a fairly poor-quality recording and much of the content cannot be viewed.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:20:02.
  - Footage: Excludables Arrival, circa 1990s; 467684 (Box 91, Cassette ref369, Box 80, Dvd ref369)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:23.
  - Footage: Detainee Arrival in Cuba, Includes Guillermo Herrera, circa 1990s; 467681 (Box 91, Cassette ref372, Box 80, Dvd ref372)
    This recording contains footage of a detainee arrival in Cuba. It features various scenes of detainees on a plane and on buses. It also features United States and Cuban officials. The original box was annotated "Guillermo," which most likely refers to Guillermo Herrera, a detainee who was separated from his family, held without charges, and eventually deported to Cuba.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:17:32.
  - Footage: Various, circa 1990s; 467679 (Box 92, Cassette ref374, Box 80, Dvd ref374)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:16:00.
  - Footage: Various, detainee interviews, family reunions (mostly Spanish, some English), circa 1990s; 467661 (Box 92, Cassette ref392, Box 80, Dvd ref392)
  - Footage: Various, B-roll, circa 1990s; 467735 (Box 90, Cassette ref318, Box 79, Dvd ref318)
    This lengthy piece of footage contains clips of the detainees arriving in Cuba and interviews with detainees on a bus. Much of this tape consists of duplicated content and background shots.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:01:00.
  - Interview Footage: Atlanta and Talladega, circa 1990s; 467721 (Box 91, Cassette ref332, Box 79, Dvd ref332)
    This tape contains footage of various interviews, most of which are in English. Footage includes: a bishop speaking about the injustices faced by the Cuban detainees; a person talking about Dr. Bolivar Martineau's medical experiments and his use of drugs; Estela Bravo touring C-cell house and interviewing the former Chief of Correctional Services [Hovington] at the Cuban repatriation unit in Talladega; and a lawyer discussing the legality of indefinite detention of the Mariel refugees and the role of Judge Marvin Shoob.
    The final 10 minutes of the recording consists of Spanish-language TV programming.
  - Interview Footage: Detainees and Guards (Spanish), circa 1990s; 467565 (Box 92, Cassette ref488, Box 81, Dvd ref488)
  - Interview Footage: Detainees, Guards (Spanish), circa 1990s; 467563 (Box 92, Cassette ref490, Box 81, Dvd ref490)
    This tape consists of interviews with prison guards detainees on bus. It appears to contain many different clips in Spanish that focus on Dr. Bolivar Martineau. The quality of the footage is intermittently poor and many scenes are difficult to view.
  - Interview Footage: Detainees and Family Members, circa 1990s; 467560 (Box 92, Cassette ref493, Box 82, Dvd ref493)
    This tape contains footage of family visits and interviews with detainees. It is mostly Spanish, but some in in English. There are moments without sound.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:51:00.
  - Interview Footage: Returning Detainees and Family Members; Dr. Bolivar Martineau and Denny McLain, circa 1990s; 467720 (Box 91, Cassette ref333, Box 79, Dvd ref333)
    The interviews with Denny McLain and Dr. Martineau featured on this video were funded by the Canadian Broadcasting System television investigative documentary program The Fifth Estate. CBS used the footage and then returned it to the Bravos for their film.
    Most of the footage involves interviews with returned detainees and their families. They largely feature discussions about the Marielitos. At around 54 minutes, there is a brief clip of Dr. Bolivar Martineau, then at 57 minutes, discussion with someone who worked at the prison with Martineau. There is a brief discussion with Denny McLain with Spanish voiceover, and then several additional minutes with Martineau.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:30:03.
  - Interview Footage: Returning Detainees and Family Members, circa 1990s; 467719 (Box 90, Cassette ref334, Box 80, Dvd ref334)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:56:01.
  - "Homeless People under Freeway", circa 1990s; 479456 (Box 49, Cassette ref1117)
  - "Hospital Psychiatrists", circa 1990s; 479497 (Box 49, Cassette ref1155)
  - "Los Excluibles": Spanish voice-over TV program (Fifth Estate), circa 1990s; 467564 (Box 92, Cassette ref489, Box 81, Dvd ref489)
    The first part is a Spanish voice-over TV program featuring footage from The Excludables. After 27 minutes there is a Spanish language TV program.
  - News Stories (Tape 32), 1992 November 28; 479490 (Box 64, Cassette ref1148)
  - News Stories (Tape 33), 1992 November 28; 479491 (Box 64, Cassette ref1149)
  - NBC News Advance, circa 1990s; 479515 (Box 50, Cassette ref1173)
  - One World Awards, 1997; TW_TAM_616_ER_3 (Box Electronic Records, Folder TW_TAM_616_ER_3)
  - Rough Footage, 1989; 479080 (Box 71, Cassette ref949, Box 86, Dvd ref949)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:04:59.
  - Talladega, Alabama: Deportation #1, circa 1990s; 479430 (Box 48, Cassette ref1091, Box 98, Dvd ref1091)
    This video features footage of Cubans detained in the U.S. Federal Penitentiary in Talladega, Alabama boarding a bus for deportation back to Cuba. The video features exterior shots of the prison, footage of the Cuban prisoners boarding a bus, and the bus traveling to the airport.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:16.
  - "Talladega Riot Archive", circa 1990s; 479463 (Box 64, Cassette ref1124)
  - Talladega #1, circa 1990s; 479492 (Box 49, Cassette ref1150)
  - Talladega #2, circa 1990s; 479469 (Box 64, Cassette ref1130)
  - Terre Haute: Prisoner Interviews, circa 1990s; 479438 (Box 48, Cassette ref1099, Box 98, Dvd ref1099)
    This video features interviews with three different Cuban prisoners at the US Federal Prison Camp in Terre Haute, Indiana. In the interviews the prisoners discuss how they came to the United States and why they were imprisoned. The interviews focus predominantly on the detention and treatment of the three men in the prisons. They also describe the political situation that has led to their indefinite incarceration, and the struggles they have faced while detained.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:17:42.
  - Terra Haute #1, 1993 November 3; 479458 (Box 63, Cassette ref1119)
  - Terra Haute #2, 1993 November 3; 479460 (Box 64, Cassette ref1121)
  - Terra Haute "3 Prisoners, Warden, Prison", circa 1990s; 479504 (Box 50, Cassette ref1162)
  - Little Havana (Miami) Signage, 1992 June 12; cuid290; 479462 (Box 61, Cassette ref1123, Box 96, Dvd ref1123)
    This brief video contains footage of signs of Cuban businesses in the Little Havana neighborhood of Miami, Florida.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:02:41.
  - "ABC News - Atlanta, Cuban inmates 6/26/86; Riots 11/2/84; Mariel boats", circa 1980s; 467786 (Box 12, Cassette ref267)
  - Martineau, Bolivar: Interview, circa 1990s; 467688 (Box 16, Cassette ref365)
  - Plane arriving (B-roll), circa 1990s; 467717 (Box 91, Cassette ref336, Box 80, Dvd ref336)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:47:00.
  - Cuba, Birmingham Airport (B-roll?), circa 1990s; 479482 (Box 49, Cassette ref1140)
  - "Demo 14 min Excludables", circa 1990s; 467415 (Box 33, Cassette ref638)
- Series VII: Cubans in Peru, 1982; 479612
  This series contains a small amount of footage related to the documentary Cubans in Peru. The1982 film presents the experiences and views of some of the Cubans who took part in the occupation of the Peruvian Embassy in Havana in 1980. Videos from this documentary include footage of refugees in Tupac Amaru Stadium, interviews with Cuban political refugees, and footage of a Peruvian doctor who saved the life of a Cuban child. The scenes of the doctor and child are featured at the end of the documentary.
  - "Cubans in Peru DV#3", 1982; cuid785; 479613 (Box 55, Cassette ref1271)
    This video is 20 minutes in length, and most likely contains footage rather than the full-length documentary.
  - Children's Hospital and Tupac Amaru Park (B-roll), circa 1990; 479644 (Box 56, Cassette ref1301, Box 98, Dvd ref1301)
    This video features exterior footage of a children's hospital and Tupac Amaru Park in Lima, Peru. This video has no audio.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:06:23.
  - Tupac Amaru Park: Footage, circa 1982; cuid786; 479657 (Box 59, Cassette ref1314, Box 96, Dvd ref1314)
    Tupac Amaru Park is a sports complex in East Lima that became a refugee camp for Cubans who were granted asylum in Peru after their 1980 occupation of the Peruvian Embassy in Havana.
    This video contains footage of Cuban exiles living in a tent city in Tupac Amaru Park in Lima, Peru. The video shows footage of concerned Peruvians speaking through a fence to the Cubans living in the park. It also includes some brief interviews with several Cubans living in the park about why they are there. Other footage features demonstrations and on-the-street interviews with Peruvians who oppose the presence of the Cuban exiles in the park as well as shots of local police in riot gear at the entrance to the park.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:31.
  - "Corvacho child Dr. Montano Peru", circa 1982; 479553 (Box 52, Cassette ref1211)
  - Peruvian Doctors: Interview about Cuban Child, circa 1982; 479564 (Box 53, Cassette ref1222, Box 98, Dvd ref1222)
    This video features an interview with two Peruvian doctors about a young Cuban boy in their care. They explain that the boy's mother had taken him from Cuba to Peru because she believed that he would get better medical care there. The doctors, however, explain that the boy has a complicated heart condition that they cannot treat. They discuss Peru's limited medical resources, and the need to send patients with more complicated medical issues to hospitals and clinics in Brazil. They explain they are only able to offer palliative care to the boy, and that he will need to go to another hospital for surgery.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:21.
  - University of San Marcos: Presentation on Embajador En Cuba, circa 1982; cuid787; 467342 (Box 36, Cassette ref711, Box 95, Dvd ref711)
    This video begins with footage of a panel discussion at the University of San Marcos with scholars and diplomats discussing the relationship between Cuba and Peru, and the book Embajador en Cuba by Peruvian Ambassador Edgardo de Habich. At the end of the panel discussion Habich speaks briefly about his book before the footage ends. Microphones used during the panel create echo sounds in the auditorium, which make audio quality poor in various places. At minute 11:43 the footage changes to a brief interview with Habich in which he discusses the occupation of Tupac Amaru Park in Lima by Cuban Refugees, and the refugee status of the Cubans in the park.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:13.
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002; 477042
  The 2001 documentary Fidel: The Untold Story combines a history of the Cuban revolution with a more personal story of its leader, Fidel Castro. Because so much of the interview footage for Fidel: The Untold Story could not be included in the initial feature-length film, Estela and Ernesto Bravo made a follow-up documentary, Anecdotes about Fidel, in 2010. It includes portions of 24 interviews and expands on the stories about Fidel Castro.
  In 2001, Fidel: The Untold Story was selected for the Toronto Film Festival and won an award for "Distinguished Achievement for Excellence in Documentary Filmmaking" at the Urbanworld Film Festival in New York.
  This series contains clips, interviews, and background footage from the documentaries Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel. The 2001 documentary Fidel: The Untold Story combines a history of the Cuban revolution with a more personal story of leader, Fidel Castro. This series contains copies of both films. It includes complete interviews and portions of interviews highlighted in the two films. They feature historians, public figures, close friends, and Castro himself, and provide a glimpse into the life and personality of the Cuban leader. Interviewees include Alice Walker, Gabriel García Márquez, Arthur Schlesinger, Ramsey Clark, Ted Turner, Nelson Mandela, Charles Rangel, George McGovern, Philip Agee, and many others who share personal anecdotes along with political and historical perspectives.
  The anecdotes come not only from well-known Americans such as Harry Belafonte, Jesse Jackson, Angela Davis, Hank Aaron, Sydney Pollack and others, but also from many Cubans who are not well known in the United States. Among them are government officials and friends of Fidel such as Juan Almeida, Melba Hernández. Alfredo Guevara, Jorge Risquet, Antonio Núñez Jiménez, Alicia Alonso, Angela Castro, and Aleida Guevara.
  This series also contains a number of interviews that are not seen in the films. They include discussions with Hortensia Bussi de Allende, the widow of Salvador Allende, and American lawyer Victor Rabinowitz.
  Footage in this series also consists of clips from the Cuban State Council Archives and various news sources. Videos containing State Council footage often represent a wide date range. Some of the footage is dated 1998 which reflects the date the material was obtained, not the actual date of the events. The original dates of the footage were not recorded. Additional footage depicts Fidel Castro at a number of public events giving speeches or speaking with world leaders. Other materials in this series include documents related to the promotion and distribution of Fidel, including contact lists, posters, correspondence related to distribution rights.
  - Fidel: The Untold Story, 2000; 590451 (Reel ref1903_01, Reel ref1903_02, Reel ref1903_03, Reel ref1903_04, Reel ref1903_05, Reel ref1903_06, Reel ref1903_07, Reel ref1903_08, Reel ref1903_09, Reel ref1903_10, Reel ref1903_11, Reel ref1903_12, Reel ref1903_13, Reel ref1903_14, Reel ref1903_15, Reel ref1903_16, Reel ref1903_17, Reel ref1903_18)
    This is a full-length version of the film Fidel: The Untold Story. The complete documentary is contained on 6 positive film reels, 6 film negative reels, and 6 sound track reels.
  - "Fidel Trailer", circa 2000; 479388 (Box 47, Cassette ref1049)
  - An Evening with Estela Bravo: Filmmaker of "Fidel: The Untold Story" and "Anecdotes about Fidel" at the Paley Center for Media, New York City, 2012 May 9; 590464 (Box 73, Dvd 16)
    A film of the event honoring Estela Bravo, focusing on the release of Anecdotes about Fidel at the Paley Center for Media. Bravo speaks with Pat Mitchell about her life and career, and responds to questions from the audience. Clips are shown from Anecdotes about Fidel; There are also clips from other films that have dealt with Cuban-American relations, such as Miami-Havana, The Cuban Excludables, and Operation Peter Pan: Flying Back to Cuba.
  - Aaron, Hank: Interview, circa 1995-2000; 477048 (Box 68, Cassette ref846, Box 83, Dvd ref846)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:42.
  - Aaron, Hank: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid291; 479247 (Box 45, Cassette ref983, Box 95, Dvd ref983)
    This video features an interview with baseball player Hank Aaron. At the beginning, Aaron briefly introduces himself and discusses his baseball career. The bulk of the interview focuses on Aaron's impression of Cuba and Fidel Castro. Aaron describes traveling to Cuba to film a documentary about Cuban baseball players, and describes the quality of education and baseball training he observed while in Cuba. He also discusses meeting Fidel Castro, and speaks specifically about Castro's athletic ability. Aaron also talks briefly about the poor diplomatic relations between Cuba and the United States, and argues that lack of trade and freedom of movement between the countries has contributed to the suffering of Cuban people and their family members in the United States.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:01.
  - Agee, Philip: Interview, 1997 March 8; 593328
    - Agee, Philip: Interview Recording, 1997 March 8; 468038; 4 items This interview is contained on 4 access DVDs (Box 4, Cassette ref15, Box 75, Dvd ref15)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 4 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:29:22; Part 2 - 00:08:00; Part 3 - 00:00:09; Part 4 - 00:01:25.